[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
uh we won't get to Bells theorem but
that's okay we can do that next
week I hope we get to entanglement all
right but we were in the midst of still
entanglement has to do with what happens
the simplest case of it is when you have
two electrons with their spins forget
the fact that electrons can move around
just worry about their spins tanglement
is what happens when you have more than
one system and uh and the kind of
interesting Quantum states that can be
made for systems which have parts to
them more than one part we're still
struggling through trying to understand
the simplest Quantum system the one bit
or the one Quantum bit system the spin
the two-state system and I wanted to
finish that up
because it will come in in a very
Central Way all of the things we are
talking about about the simple spin
system the last time we talked about uh
what happens if you're interested in the
component of spin along some axis which
is neither 3 two or one but along some
arbitrary axis and the arbitrary axis
can be represented by a unit Vector a
unit pointer a unit
pointer uh that has
components
N1 N2 and three incidentally um okay so
here's my coordinates in space I guess
I've called this one one this one two
this one three and I may lapse every now
and then into calling One X 2 Y and 3 Z
so uh uh keep in mind that's I've tried
not to I tried to keep a consistent
notation in my notes but I do have that
habit of sometimes going back and forth
from 1 2 and 3 to x y and
z
um and then if you have a an
ordinary vector Vector in space not this
unit Vector in particular but some other
Vector
yes is that right-handed or not I
intended it to be right-handed but I can
uh uh
X I I I I think so but I almost my
shoulder is broken and I don't think I
can do
it it doesn't matter one two and I mean
it it does matter but uh is it right
handed or isn't it no it's left-handed
okay so so then we have to have y going
into the
board all right then we have to have y
going into the board but
uh yeah
yeah
indeed but my broken shoulder is
limiting
my my orientation all right now if you
have some physical Vector thing that you
that you can measure in particular a
thing that we've represented as having
components Sigma Sigma X or Sigma 1
Sigma 2 and sigma 3 this is supposed to
be some physically measurable little
Magnetic Moment or spin
Vector it has components along the one
two and three axes we can call them
Sigma 1 Sigma 2 and sigma 3 and we have
called them Sigma 1 Sigma 2 and sigma 3
those are observable quantities and we
represent them by matrices but for the
moment forget that they're matrices
uh if we're interested in the component
of Sigma along the arbitrary axis
in then what we're interested in is the
dot product of Sigma with n and to
indicate a unit Vector it's conventional
to put a little hat on top of
it if it's a unit Vector then let's just
write down a couple of
equations n1^ 2 + N2 2 plus n3^ 2 is
equal to
1 okay that's the definition of unit
vector and sigma. N this is the
ordinary space dot product not the inner
product of two abstract vectors
representing States but just the
ordinary dotproduct in space of a vector
that we can measure whose components are
measurable quantities and the unit
Vector n then this is by definition N1 1
Sigma 1 plus N2 Sigma 2 plus N3 Sigma 3
but now each of the sigmas is itself a
matrix the ends are just numbers the
direction cosiness of some direction is
what they are the direction cosiness of
some
direction and uh but the sigmas are
matrices and so this whole thing is
itself a matrices or operators if I want
to be really technically correct uh
linear operators but let's just think of
them as matrices and then remembering
what's let's write down what the Matrix
is okay so Sigma 3 remember what Sigma 3
is it's the Matrix with a one and a
minus one so that means we would
multiply it by N3 and put N3 here and
minus N3
here uh Sigma 1 has a one over here and
a one over here so we would put an n one
over here and an N1 over here and then
Sigma 2 has a minus I and a plus I so we
would write
plus I and let me make this
bigger N1 + I
N2 and then down here it would be N1 no
sorry minus I
N2 and here it be N1 minus plus I
N2 and then minus N3 over here notice
that it's
hermiss the diagonal elements are real
the off diagonal elements are complex
conjugates of each other that makes it
her
Mission and I'm going to just
uh make a little
notation a may or may not use it very
much but it's a standard notation to
write that N1 minus I I
N2 is equal to n minus and N1 + I
N2 is equal to n plus just
definition okay
uh let me write another interesting
simple equation if you multiply n plus
oh oh then we can just write that this
is equal to and simplify the expression
N3 n minus n Plus minus
N3 that's the Matrix sigma.
n and it's supposed to be an observable
something we can measure we measure it
by putting the electron or suddenly
turning on a large magnetic field
oriented along the N
axis and then checking whether it does
or doesn't emit a photon if it doesn't
emit a photon then it
has positive component of sigma.
in okay now one thing that we checked
last time I believe we checked last time
was that for any N sigma. N
squared is equal to
1 you can check
that either by multiplying this matrix
by itself and then using the fact that
n12 plus N2 sare + n 32 =
1 or you can check it
from the fact that each one of the well
you can check it from properties of the
sigma matrices from the sigma matrices
themselves I think I did I work that out
last time yeah and it follows from the
fact that any one of the sigmas times
any one of the other
sigmas is equal to minus Sigma J Sigma
I for I not equal to
J so Sigma 1 Sig Sigma 2 is minus Sigma
2 Sigma 1 and you can check that easily
that the that this is the square is
equal to one now um I'm not going to
prove this right now it's a very very I
can't prove every single little detail
of everything we do because it would
take forever so here and there if I say
something that uh that you don't know
usually it's it usually means it's
something that takes about a half a line
to prove and you can and you can prove
it uh think of it a homework assignment
okay so if sigma. n² is equal to 1 well
if a number squared is equal to 1 that
means that the number is either plus or
minus one right if a matrix squared is
equal to one it means its igen values
are all plus or minus
one so sigma. n in fact has two for any
n has two igen values 1 + 1 and 1 equal
to minus one as you might expect
corresponding to the uh to the two
possibilities that when you measure the
spin along that axis you either get plus
or minus so for sigma. n^2 is equal to
one that's one fact another little
algebraic fact which is kind of neat if
you multiply these I don't know if it's
neat it's it's true that's all if it's n
plus * n minus that's equal to n1^ 2 +
N2 squared oh notice that n plus and N
minus are complex conjugates of each
other so n plus n minus
oops m + n minus is equal to n1^ 2 + N2
2 now this is
a uh true
statement all right let me add to this
plus n3^ 2ar and then subtract n3^
2 I haven't changed it and now I see
that n plus n minus is equal to 1 - n3^
squared oneus one
minus I don't want to square the whole
thing I only want to square the
N3 that's a that's a a
useful little algebraic fact that if you
do the homework which I'm going to
assign for you you will use over and
over
again but it's it's a it it's uh not
anything deep it's just a little
algebraic fact
okay here is the question I ultimately
the question I want to ask is the
following supposing I Orient a spin I
prepare a spin by putting it in a large
magnetic field waiting for it to Decay
or not Decay and I force it into a
particular along a particular axis
supposing I force it to be along the N
AIS then I me measure the component of
the spin along a different axis let's
call it the ma AIS here's the ma axis
over
here what's the probability that if
I make the spin with its spin along the
N AIS and then measure it along the ma
AIS I will find that it's plus along the
ma AIS and of course the opposite
probability that it's minus along the ma
axis this this is the central kind of
question that quantum mechanics deals
with uh for the simple half for the
simple spin electron spin this is about
the only interesting question that you
can
ask
question
okay uh you could also of course ask
supposing you oriented along the ma AIS
and measure it on the N axis by symmetry
it's pretty clear that they should be
equal to each
other and furthermore you might even ECT
that the rotational symmetry of the
world should mean that the answer only
depends on the angle between n and M
that would be a nice thing to discover
and in fact it's true the answer only
depends on the angle between them that's
going to be part of your homework
assignment but how do you do it okay so
we have to go back then to the basic um
probability uh postulate about quantum
mechanics that what we first do is
calculate the igen vectors of sigma. N
and the igen vectors of sigma. M now we
first find the igen vector of sigma. n
that corresponds to spin pointing
definitely along this
axis and then we take the inner product
with the igen vector of sigma. M
corresponding to spin pointing along
this direction so we could write this
out uh let's let's make a
notation
okay question no yes yeah we just told
us that Sigma 1 2 and three are
spin operators does quantum mechanics
tell us that or did
some well it it's no single experiment
it's the whole accumulated I
mean
um how to say this there was a whole lot
L of data about this you could do this
experiment over and over and over again
and
eventually you would
discover that the probabilities that
that there are probabilities that's an
experimental fact that the probabilities
are given by the formulas we're going to
write down that was something that was
deduced by guessing it was guessing it
was brilliant guessing um but
uh
and who guessed it it wasn't any single
person it was a buildup from the work
first of all starting with Einstein who
was the first to realize that quantum
theory involved
probabilities and then Bourne and then
Heisenberg and then durak so there was a
series of steps in which all of this was
eventually discovered now nobody nobody
has ever understood what what the hell
Heisenberg was thinking when he invented
Matrix
mechanics nobody understands or what the
um mystical experience or what he was
smoking or what but uh but uh he
did and uh I think you simply have to
take quantum mechanics as defined by
matrix mechanics as an experimental fact
it uh it can't be derived from anything
it's not something you can derive from
uh from anything else it's a set of uh
empirical facts which are summarized by
this calculus of probabilities
okay so let's let's first invent a
notation first of all I'm going to
invent a notation for the igen vector of
sigma. n equals + one I'll just call it
the
vector the igen vector of sigma. n with
igen value + one what does it satisfy it
satisfies that sigma.
n equals
if you apply Sigma do into
it you just get the same Vector back
this whole elaborate thing here is just
uh is just um a statement that I'm
talking about the igen vector of sigma.
n with igen value + one if I apply
sigma. n to such an igen Vector I just
get one times the same
vector
okay that's that's the igen vector
corresponding to a
state we could call it uh we can call it
an igen State the word igen state is
also used all the time this is the igen
state of sigma. n such that sigma. n if
you measure it is definitely equal to
plus one we can do the same for sigma.
m sigma. m on the state Sigma M =
+1 also equals Sigma
M this equal here is not an equals it's
just part of the notation labeling uh
the uh the
vector okay I could have used the
simpler notation all right so what do we
have to do the first step is to
construct these vectors to find out what
the igen vectors of sigma. n are and
sigma. n and then when you've done that
you construct what is called the
probability
amplitude first step is the probability
amplitude that's the inner
product
between the prepared
State and the final outcome whose
probability you're interested in sigma.
m equal 1 all right this is the
probability amplitude that if you create
an electron with its spin along the N
axis and then you measure it along the
ma AIS that you get one that you get
plus that you get plus one this is not
the probability this is the probability
amplitude to get the probability this is
a complex number in general you square
it you multiply it by its complex
conjugate which is labeled by two bars
and a squared the absolute value of it
squared that's the probab ility we can
call that the
probability that I don't want to write
all this out it's the probability that
if sigma. n is equal to one and then you
measure sigma. M you'll get one as
opposed to minus
one okay that's the kind of thing that
quantum mechanics calculates it's that's
exactly what uh quantum mechanics does
in every single case it asks a question
what is the probability that you'll get
a certain outcome come about a
particular variable given that you've
prepared the state in some way perhaps
involving some other
variable as yeah and
T okay so we could we could
then right the
probability that if sigma. n equal
1 then
sigma. m equal
1 the probability in general will be
less than one well let's let's let's
think of some cases if n and M are equal
then obviously the probability is one if
n and M are opposite directions then
that's just the question what's the
probability if the spin is up then then
it's down well Z must be zero so we
should find that what about at
90°
a half anywhere as in the plane if m is
in the plane perpendicular to n we would
expect to get the probability being a
half and that's that's true but how do
we how do we justify it how do we
actually calculate it so I'm going to
take you through the calculation of the
igen
vectors but then you are going to go
home and take their inner product I'll
take their inner product but then you'll
Square it and boil it and cook it and uh
stamp on it and cry and it's it's an
ugly little calculation it's not a
pleasant one now it's not very hard it
took me about 15 minutes but I used a
lot of tricks which mean it took me a
lot longer than it will take you without
any
tricks
uh okay so let's find the igen vector
now first of all when you start looking
for igen vectors we're going to try to
solve the problem sigma. n where is it
it's N3 minus
N3 n minus n
plus that's sigma. n and we're going to
look for a
vector Alpha
Beta such that we get Alpha Beta
back now in the first round I'm not
going to worry about normalizing the
vector later on we can normalize the
vector
uh normalizing it means multiplying it
by some constant so that the sums of the
squares add up to one but for the moment
let's not worry about that and if I
don't normalize the
vector also another thing I don't think
I've ever mentioned
it all of the physical quantities in
quantum
mechanics are
insensitive to
multiplying the vectors any one of the
vectors by a phase a phase means a
complex number of magnitude one and the
reason is because all of the physical
quantities you always complex conjugate
them and square it and the complex
conjugate are of and a number whose
magnitude is one number like e to the I
Theta it will not enter into any
probability that you ever calculate so
if you take a vector and you multiply it
by the number e to the I Theta you have
changed nothing about its uh its
properties
because you always wind up
multiplying a quantity by its complex
conjugate so that's something to keep in
mind that uh that you should normalize
the vector but multiplying both the top
and the bottom here by the same e to the
I Theta doesn't change anything all
right but the upshot of that is we can
arbitrarily for example choose Alpha to
be one uh if we don't care about
normalizing the vector and we don't care
about its phase then there's no loss of
generality in just choosing Alpha to be
one and I'll do it and then later we'll
come back and normalize it so what
happens if we choose Alpha let's let's
choose Alpha to be one and then I'm
going to call the lower entry here
Z and I want to get back one
Z
question is what the the question is
what does Z have to be what ises the
numerical value of Z all right so let's
read it off let's work out the equation
let's take the top component that's N3 *
1 + n minus * Z N3 * 1 + n minus * Z
that has to be equal to
1 that's reading off the top component
of the left hand side and setting it
equal to the top component of the right
right hand side now you can do the same
with a bottom component you'll get
exactly the same equation for
Z okay so I won't even bother we
obviously have enough equations here to
find Z we don't need to write the second
equation okay so let's just solve it we
can subtract N3 we get n minus Z is
equal to 1 - N3 and then divide by n
minus
and we have
found we've now found an igen
Vector of sigma. N and here it is I'll
write it out now it's
equal to
1 1-
N3 Over N
minus now it's not normalized it's not
normalized to normalize it we have to
multiply it by some number
[Music]
some some number let's just call it C
well let's just we have to multiply at
something so that this so that the uh
the sums of the squares add up to one
all right now what do we actually have
to do to be more precise we have to make
the inner product of this Vector with
itself be equal to one let's see what
the inner product of the vector with
itself is so let's first write the row
Vector the corresponding row Vector 1 1
1 - N3 now shall I write n minus down
here conjugate and the conjugate is n
plus okay that's the row vector and If I
multiply this by the column Vector 1 1 -
N3 Over N Over N
minus then what I'll get is 1 *
plus 1 minus
N3 squar Over N plus n minus did I do
that
right which is
what yeah let's uh let's work it out
let's work it
out uh let's multiply 1 by n plus n
minus so this becomes n plus and
minus
plus one when I Square this out I'll get
one + n3^
2ar minus t N3 is that
right am I doing this
right and then we have to divide
that by n plus n minus I'm just going to
take you a little ways into this
calculation now what is n plus n
minus that's uh where did we have it n
plus n minus is 1 - n3^
2ar and so plus n3^ 2ar this just gives
us and plus and minus is 1 - n3^
2 the the N3 squares
cancel the ones add and you get
2 - t
N3 Over N plus n
minus is that
right I think that's
right
can simplify it a little bit
further yeah this is 1 - n3^ squ
downstairs I'm not going to do all the
algebra I'm just going to take you a
little
ways
H yeah yeah yeah yeah so this is first
of all there are two outside then
there's a 1 - N3 in the numerator and
then in the denominator that's 1 - n3^
2 it's 1 - N3 2 which is 1 - N3 * 1 +
N3 right so we take 1 - N3 * 1 plus N3
and don't worry if you don't if you're
not following because I'm going to make
you do it over for homework all right
and then we cancel out the 1 minus N3
all right we get an answer the answer is
2 / 1 +
N3 well was that that was the that was
the inner product of the vector with
itself right and we didn't get one
that's bad that's bad we haven't
normalized the vector what do we have to
do to the vector to normalize
it we have to multiply it not by the
square root of this but by the square
root of one over this we want to kill we
want to cancel this two / 1 + N3 and so
we have to multiply the vector the igen
vector by by the inverse square root so
here is the normalized igen vector and
the homework of course is to check this
and uh to check that it is the
normalized vector over two time 1 1us N3
Over N
minus that's the normalized igen
vector corresponding to measuring the
spin along the N axis
the same thing is true along the ma AIS
except Wherever You See n you put
M Let's uh let's rewrite this let's
actually put the square roots on the
inside uh Square < TK of 1 + N3 over 2
and then 1 - N3 this looks too comp this
is more complicated than it really has
to be but uh
1 + N3 sare < TK /
2 that's the normalized igen vector now
what about the other half of the
calculation the other half of the
calculation is the other Vector the igon
vector of sigma. M and that's easy all
we have to do is replace n by m and
complex
conjugate so the appropriate row Vector
looks very similar
Square < TK of 1 +
M3 and then in the second entry 1 - M3
now instead of M minus we'll put M plus
because it's complex conjugated and then
Square < TK of 1 + M3 /
2 what do we do with this mess we take
the inner product the inner product I'm
not going to do it we're I'm going to
tell you what the answer is is we
multiply this one by this one oh there's
a two right two nobody tell me two we
multiply this one by this one and we add
this one times this one it looks like an
Unholy mess and it is
okay
but if you use a little bit of
algebra and you just go through
it uh brute force it will take you 10
minutes if you use all the tricks it'll
take you 15
minutes
so uh and you just use you use over and
over again the fact that n plus n minus
is 1 - n3^ 2ar you fiddle it I'm going
to tell you what the answer is not for
this not for this in itself but we have
to do one more thing with this what's
the next thing we have to do with
it zero what's that has to be zero why
does it have to be
zero why this is M this is n
what there's nothing orthogonal about
them if this were in this would be a
vector times its
a what are you
saying if M and N were the same the
inner product would be one that's what
we took care of to make sure
of no no no they're not
orthogonal what do we want to do with
them what we want to do with
it that's okay Square it take it times
its complex conjugate it times its
complex conjugate so we take this inner
product we multiply it out it's a big
mess but it's just it's just a mess of
uh n's and M's and we take the whole
thing when we get it and we multiply it
by its complex
conjugate and you sit and you calculate
and you calculate and you calculate and
you uh
you can even try to throw it onto a
computer and see what you get using
Mathematica or something or whatever you
like however you like to do it but the
answer is incredibly
simple
uh I have yet to be able to find a one
line way to prove to to demonstrate the
answer I always have to do it go through
the whole
thing uh I'm absolutely convinced that
there's a oneline argument but I can
never find it anyway the answer is one
plus N1
M1 plus N2
M2 plus N3
M3 /
2 or 1 plus n.
M over
two that's the whole
answer after you finished it has n's and
M's all of the components all over the
place and it's simp boils down
eventually to this expression now what
is n.m anybody know what n.m
is it's the cosine of the angle between
them it's the cosine let's call this
Theta n
m the angle between the N AIS and the ma
AIS and so this is
just 1 + cosine of theta n m /
2 now first of all one interesting thing
about it is that it only depends on the
angle between n and
M that means you would get the same
result if you rotated the whole
experiment okay that's an interesting
fact uh and it's an important fact of
course it's what has to do with
rotational invariance of physics that
the axes didn't
matter uh that if you rotated the whole
experiment you would get the the same
answer it's
also symmetric in n and M since it only
depends on the angle between them and
the angle between them it doesn't matter
whether you write n first or M first
it's exactly the same answer if you
interchange n and M that's
interesting but let's see what uh what
it gives for various situations first of
all supposing n and M are in the same
direction if n and M are in the same
direction then cosine then Theta is zero
all right this is the angle is zero and
cosine of 0 is 1 1 + 1 is 2 2 / two is 1
so the first thing it
says is that if you prepare the electron
pointing along the N axis and then you
measure it along the N axis you will
definitely find it up you made it up you
measure it and you find it up that's a
good thing what about if n and M are
opposite to each other not perpendicular
but
opposite in other words then Theta is
180° cosine of 180° is min-1 1 + -1 is
zero okay that says that if you prepare
the
electron along the N axis and then look
and ask whether it's it spin is along
the minus n axis you'll get zero
probability in other words if it's
pointing that way it's definitely not
pointing that way that's a good thing
what if Theta is 90° and it doesn't
matter notice it doesn't
matter if n is fixed M uh M can be uh
anywhere in space as long as its angle
is fixed so it could be on a cone but in
any case if uh if Theta is 90° what do
you get cosine of 90° is uh is zero huh
cosine of 90 degrees is zero and so you
just get 1/2 which is what we expected
but now we actually know the
interpolating formula the formula that's
good for any angle and this is the most
primitive but basic quantum mechanical
calculation that uh that quantum
mechanics does so notice I mean think
think this is a remarkable achievement
we have some strange theory in where
whenever we measure the spin along any
given axis it's either Plus or minus and
nothing in between and yet there's
something about this system which
doesn't care about the axes you can
Orient the spin along any axis and
measure it along any other axis and
instead of getting fractional answers
you get fractional probabilities for for
the result and this is the fractional
probability okay are there any questions
up till now or we could plot this
function incidentally as a function of
angle
at uh 180 degrees it goes to zero at 0
degrees it's one and it looks like
whoops put 180 degrees over
here it just looks like
that so we know the answer now to any
question that you can meaningfully ask
about a single Quantum
bit how do we know that's the same
electron we just have one
electron do know
that well we we we build us a cavity and
put some sealed walls to prevent
anything from going in and going out and
uh we
uh we do find that that electron stays
in there we can measure the electric
charge by measuring the outgoing
electric flux we find it doesn't change
so yeah we can measure the uh the
electric charge for example and uh and
uh what's
that
matter if we do the same thing to every
one of the electrons is that what you
mean yeah yeah that's right and and in
practice we can either do one of two
things you don't measure a probability
in order to measure a probability you
have to do an experiment repeatedly okay
you have to do the same experiment over
and over again you can do it in one of
two ways you can do this take the same
electron and continuously repeat the
experiment so you put your electron you
put your big magnetic field along the N
axis line up that electron and then
measure it along the ma AIS then when
you finished you put back your big
electric field along the N axis line it
up again and do the experiment over and
over and over and over again you you
have you can do that or you can get
yourself a whole bunch of
electrons and do a million identical
experiments doing one experiment on each
electron you should get and you do get
the same answer okay you do get the same
answer for the probability in the case
that you have a million electrons the
probability simply means the ratio of
the number of ups and
downs um within the margin error of
course there always margins of error uh
you're saying that the million electrons
are all covered in one experiment well
you could you can do an experiment in
which you take a million electrons line
them all up along the N axis okay okay
you fellas line up along the N axis put
a big magnetic field on each one and
then measure each one's spin along the
ma axis some will be plus some will be
minus okay but the ratio of the number
of pluses and minuses will measure the
probability for plus and minus actually
they just all have to have the same the
same okay but if you really want to yeah
right but that that that's that's indeed
so but yes that's true but uh uh let's
uh let's be let's be a little bit purist
about it and say we do the same repeated
experiment over and over but yes you're
right yeah if you use one electron how
many times
always wait say it again how many phons
can
Elon endless numbers endless numbers
it's the energy fed in by turning on the
magnetic field okay when you turn on
that magnetic field if the spin is in
the wrong direction you have to do a
little more work to turn on the magnetic
field than if it's in the right
direction and it's that energy which is
effectively the uh the photon that's
emitted so there's no limit to the
number of times you can do this
experiment uh you you define the sigma
in terms of the three sign matri yes and
one of the side effects of this was that
you went from having nice
clean vectors to ug look vors
yeah right also ugliness is in the eye
of the beholder of course so I
mean well yeah I mean it is one of these
days I'm going to find a trick for this
calculation so that it's not so ugly but
uh the question is is this a general
characteristic of that type of Matrix
operator basis yeah uh let me put it
this way there's another way to
prove that the answer only depends on
the angle between them but that will
take us into unitary matrices and things
and we'll get into that we will get into
that and symmetries and interesting
things that we haven't gotten to yet but
I could do just a simple example I could
for example take in to be up supposing I
took in to be up let's see what we get
if we take in to be up okay so um if n
is up M doesn't the M Vector stays the
same right
m is just some arbitrary direction right
but let's take the in Vector to be up
then this is just one
Z okay now the answer is
easy it's just this times this plus this
times this but that's zero all right so
the probability amplitude the thing that
you square is just the square root of 1
+
M3 over
two we Square
it and what do we get we get one plus M3
/
2 but M3 is just the cosine of the angle
of M of M with the third axis right
that's what M3 is M3 is a direction
cosine in this case the direction cosine
of M and so it actually is just
cosine of that angle so if we're willing
to pick particular directions and in
particular if some of the the directions
are along the axis one of the
axes uh then it's usually very simple
it's still not a un Matrix which is not
a unit
Matrix first of all I don't see any
Matrix here this was not a matrix this
was absolute value squared it means
times its complex
conjugate can Coates wait yes
yes
yeah yeah yeah one of the matrices was
just Sigma 3 by itself which has igen
vectors one Z and
01 all right so I chose this igen
Vector right in particular we should
check that that really is the igen
vector supposing N3 is plus one
supposing it's + one okay okay N3 being
+ one just means that n is along the
third axis pointing up right 1 + N3
would be two two / two is 1 so this just
becomes one that's gone one is up here
but 1 minus N3 that would be zero right
if N3 is one this would be zero so in
fact for the special case where N3 or
where n is along the third axis the igen
vector is just just one zero and it's
the igen vector then of just plain old
Sigma
3 okay good so you can always choose the
coordinates want well no no no you're
you're right you're right but there was
nothing from the start that guaranteed
that we were going to be able to find a
um find rotational invariance in the
problem so one of the things we prove by
doing this calculation is that the
answer is rotationally invariant if we
had independent reason to believe that
the answer was rotationally invariant
then we just pick an axis I
know well I just picked this crazy set
of three sigma matrices where did I get
them from
yeah yeah
yeah right but but we're we're we're
touching on the question of symmetries
now namely the symmetry of a system
under
rotation and we and there's a whole
subject of symmetry and quantum
mechanics which we will come to which is
an inter you know which is interesting
on its own and I I I I prefer to defer
that discussion about picking axes until
we until we until we have a language to
speak about it in at the moment uh at
the moment let's just take it as a boon
as a uh gift from God that the answer
came out to be only dependent on the
angle between the uh between the um
N&M
yeah
whoops I'm G to get in big
troubling
depends
yeah perspec how we explain why is it
that I tell you let's wait a little
while let's wait a little while while
that is the question of symmetries and
what's and how symmetries work in
quantum mechanics and uh it's a step
that I don't want to do right now
because I do want to get to entanglement
and and getting entangled in
uh they're good questions they're very
good questions but I I would prefer just
to say at this point it's just luck luck
of the draw we pick the right
matrices all right um first of all when
you just get something ah leave it just
no no no we we let me just get the
cookie out of the way that's the most
important
thing
uh yeah another important idea that
we've sort of mentioned but never really
focused on is when you measure a thing
you get an answer but then you leave the
system in some new state in other words
when you measure something you go into
the system you interact with it and you
change its state in general in
particular if you measure a particular
quantity and you get an
answer that answer corresponds to some
igen value you leave the system in an
igen Vector with that igen value so if
you if you measure the spin along the ma
AIS to be up you leave the system in the
state where the spin along the ma axis
is up you started with a state along the
N axis you measured it by putting it
into this large magnetic field and you
leave it in the state corresponding to
the measurement that you've made right
so that's an important idea that not
only is it a measurement but it's a kind
of filter which Le like a like a
polarizer that polarizes
photons um you measure the polarization
of a photon by sending it through a PO
polarizer but at the same time you also
leave it in the state of polarization
corresponding to that polarizer same
idea here that uh that the electron is
left in an igen state of whatever it is
you
measured corresponding to the value that
measured
okay let's see oh there's another
interesting
theorem
well let's uh
yeah can you measure can you do a single
measurement or simultaneously two
measurements that measured both Sigma 1
and sigma 2
simultaneously can you do a measurement
which measures both of them and uh
doesn't screw up somehow and the answer
is no and the answer is very s the
reason is very
simple the igen vectors if you measure
Sigma 1 and you get an answer and you
measure Sigma 2 and you get an answer
remember the rule is that you leave the
system in an igen State corresponding to
that
measurement
okay
okay you've got your a just
carry all right now the problem is there
are no there are no igen vector s in
common between Sigma n and sigma M they
have different igen vectors they are not
in common uh therefore you cannot
measure them both simultaneously because
you cannot leave them in a state which
is both an igen Vector of sigma. N and
sigma. M they just are no no uh no igen
vectors which which they share right so
no it is not possible to measure them
but an interesting question is what is
the condition the mathematical condition
that you can measure two quantities
simultaneously and the answer is that
they had better have all the same igen
vectors that the igen vectors of one of
them had better be exactly the same as
the igen vectors of the other one
because if you measure them and you get
an
answer uh then the answer has to be uh
an igen value and the igen values
corespond to distinct igen vectors and
the only way that you can ever measure
two quantities simultaneously and be
sure that you'll get an ERS is if they
share all the same igen
vectors who was
that if two matrices share all the same
igen vectors they have a
property the property is they
commute okay now this is again something
I do want to get to uh where I'm going
tonight but uh let me write that as a
theorem on the Blackboard you can attemp
to measure what's that
meas meas and get the right answer or
they don't one another you don't you can
do the measurement but well how are you
going to how would you measure Sigma X
and sigma y simultaneously you can do
the physical experim
how remember you measure Sigma X by
putting it into a large magnetic field
along the xaxis you measure Sigma y by
along the y axis well you put it into a
magnetic field which is both along the x
axis and the Y AIS but then you'll be
measur you know which you'll be
measuring uh not Sigma X or Sigma y but
Sigma along a 45 degree angle you'll be
measuring something
different so the answer is you'll never
think of a way of even measuring it but
that's that's good because the
mathematics says you shouldn't be able
to all right the condition if I have two
matrices that they have all common igen
vectors I'm going to write the
condition and either look up the proof
of it prove it yourself it really is a
oneliner this really is a one well maybe
two lines at
most but if two matrices A and
B have all the same igen vectors let's
call them Alpha sub I these are the
various igen
vectors
no that's not what I want to
write Lambda
I this is the I igen Vector
wow Alpha I there and another Matrix has
exactly the same igen
vectors but perhaps different igen
values let's call them mu mui * Alpha I
in other words the same set of Alphas
are the vectors of both matrices then
you can measure them simultaneously the
two quantities if they have the same
igen
vectors uh and under those
circumstances there's a theorem that's a
oneliner as I
said it says that a * B is equal to B *
a
or in mathematical term well or a minus
b a b minus ba a is equal to zero
remember the order that you multiply
matrixes is important when you multiply
matrices it's important if the matrices
commute that means it doesn't matter
which order you write them in then all
of the igen vectors are simultaneous uh
igen vectors of the two operators that's
a theorem necessary and sufficient
condition for all of the igen vectors to
be in to be the same are that the
matrices
commute commute means you can
interchange the order another way of
writing the same thing the mathematical
notation for ab minus ba is to just
write them in a
bracket not a bracket
a a commutator this is called a
commutator and it means AB minus
ba if two operators commute you can
measure them sign simultaneously because
they have exactly the same igen vectors
that's a theorem and uh as I said it
really is a one or two line theorem you
know how a acts on just multiplies by
number and then you know how B acts it
also multiplies by a number and so you
can easily figure out what the product
of A and B is on any Vector on any igen
vector and from that you can conclude uh
you can make your conclusion so I I
don't want to go through the proof of
that that because it take us astray but
um I do want to get
to
okay there is one more theorem one more
theorem about the simple Spin and it's a
very interesting theorem and an
important theorem this one is really
quite important it's a theorem about the
single
spin what it
says is that no matter what state you
write down what Vector in other words
any
Vector you write down Alpha
Beta with presumably Alpha star Alpha
plus beta star beta equals 1 assume
that so that's
normalized no matter what state you
write down there is always some
direction of
space such that if the electron is in
this Spa direct if the electron is in
this state then the spin along that
direction is definitely Plus in other
words any Vector that you write down is
an igen Vector of some sigma.
n given in Alpha and beta you can
find a direction in space such that this
is an igen
Vector let's write it the alphab
beta equals Alpha
Beta any alpha or
beta in this case the problem is not
finding the igen
vector given an N you can look for an
igen Vector this is the reverse problem
given the state of an electron can you
find the direction along which that
electron is definitely up and the answer
is yes and the simplest way to prove it
it is to count the think of this as
equations Alpha and beta are fixed
numbers okay fixed complex numbers this
is an equation for the components N1 N2
and
N3
okay uh the simplest way to prove it is
simply to count the number of equations
and the number of variables that you
have the number of equations is the same
as the number of variables
uh basically there are two equations one
for the top component and one for the
bottom component how many components of
n are
there
yes so there are two variables yeah no
there's only two
variables there's two variables two real
variables because nx2 plus n y^2 plus
nz2 is equal to 1 in other words N is a
unit vector and so the number of
variables that it takes to describe it
are two angles longitude and latitude
okay on a sphere so there are two
variables there are two equations two
unknowns and uh and the number of
unknowns and the number of equations is
the same you can check that and so
there's always an N there is always an N
given any Vector so what that what that
says is that if you take an if you
here's the way you might do the
experiment you've made an electron in
some definite State okay
but you're not sure what direction it
corresponds to right you're not sure you
you did something with the
electron and you weren't clear uh
somebody you all you know is somebody
put a magnetic field on it and lined it
up along some direction or I don't even
know what they did whatever they did
they did something and they left the
electron in some
State and we would like to find out if
there is a definite Direction along
which the spin is up so here's what we
do we first of of all make a whole bunch
of replicas of the same experiment so we
have a whole bunch of electrons all
identically
prepared all identically prepared now we
measure now we use the and how many of
them 100 zillion of them we're going to
use the first 100 million to find out
which direction the spin is pointing and
then we'll check all the rest of them
and check and make sure that they really
are all pointing in the same direction
so what you can do is you can measure
the spin of the first one along some
uh uh arbitrary axis you can measure the
first hundred of them along that axis if
they all point up along that axis it
sounds like there's a good bet that uh
that they're up along that axis and then
you measure all the rest of them and you
find them all up but you might find that
if you measure along the z-axis you'll
find some up and some down okay if you
measure the first 100 of them and you
find some up and some down change
direction a little bit change the
direction of your magnet a little bit
and check another hundred of
them if you still find there are some up
and some down change the direction of
the magnet again keep changing the
direction of the magnet until you find
the direction where all 100 or all
thousand uh test electrons are
definitely up then when you found that
you will find that all the rest of them
are up okay uh a thousand may not be a
big enough number you may have to use
10,000 but
um but that's the idea there is for any
state of an electron no matter how you
prepare it if you prepare it carefully
there will
be a
direction along which it is definitely
pointing in that direction
yeah the two degrees of freedom right
the N has two degrees of
freedom Alpha and beta are both complex
right good very good so it sounds like
there are four it sounds like there are
four right we have the normal we have
the
normalization but we also have the
freedom to change the
phase we also have the freedom to change
the phase so there's no the the phase
drops out of the equation
also don't you need an value
one well we're looking we're looking for
we're looking for a direction such that
the igen value is
one we're searching for some direction
that the igen value is one and this
gentleman over here asked exactly the
right question started counting
variables how many equations are there
well there's as many equations as there
are components of Alpha and beta okay
there are four complex
components this equation reduces it down
to three but then the fact that uh that
the uh the the overall phase of the wave
function that you can mult that uh that
uh uh doesn't matter in this equation
either in other words multiplying it by
both sides by e to the I Theta doesn't
matter and so really there are only two
degrees of
freedom in writing down a uh a complex
Vector for an electron two degrees of
freedom two unknown two two variables
here two independent interesting
variables here two of them here and so
the number of equations is the same as
the number of unknowns does Thea any
physical meaning the Theta the overall
phase of the wave function does not have
or this is called a wave function the
overall phase of the state Vector does
not have a physical
significance why not because uh because
whenever you calculate any physical
probability you always wind up
multiplying it by its complex conjugate
when you multiply by a complex conjugate
the phase goes away
okay so the answer is there are
two
variables two physically interesting
variables that go into defining the the
state of an electron and they're in
onetoone correspondence with the two
physical variables that Define a
directionality in space so you can make
a correspondence between uh between the
components here and directions of
space all right that's true of single
electrons everything I
said now I am going to continue because
well let's
see no we can take a we can take a five
minute
break Let's uh let's let's try to get to
entanglement
today to get to entanglement we have to
think about
I'll tell you something I went to a
school a middle school and I taught a
bunch of 10year olds about string theory
and extra dimensions and all that
stuff it was kind of
interesting teaching them was very much
like teaching you guys it's no no no no
no no no it was it was it was it was
they're unafraid to ask questions
they're boisterous they're fun to teach
it's the people in the undergraduates
who are just terrified of asking a
question just no fun to teach one kid
asked me a brilliant question he said
the neutrinos there's all these
neutrinos around are those are things
that give me
headaches but you know it really has the
same
feel we're going to begin now studying
pairs of
electrons to to get to the basic idea of
entanglement all we need is two
electrons but just before we do that I
want to make a
table a table of the action of the sigma
matrices I just want to write
Sigma Sigma one on up what does Sigma
one on up
give Sigma one is the Matrix which
interchanges up and down it's off
diagonal and it means that it
interchanges it takes up to
down Sigma 1 on down equals
up Sigma 2 what does Sigma 2 do on
up well Sigma 2 and sigma 1 are very
similar except there's an i in there and
a minus sign so actually what Sigma 2 on
up does anybody
know well it gives you it gives you down
again but it gives you down with an i in
front of it and sigma 2 on down gives
you minus I * up you can check that just
from the matrices and finally Sigma 3
what does sigma3 do when it hits
up just goes up up is an igen Vector of
Sigma 3 with I value plus one so it just
gives up and sigma 3
on down gives minus down because it's an
igen Vector with minus sign this is um
this is an abstract uh representation of
the sigma matrices well it's not
abstract it's concrete but uh but it's a
it's a it has the same content that the
uh The Matrix structure has now let's
come to pair of
electrons and when I speak about a pair
of electrons once again I'm not
concerned with their position I imagine
that they're nailed down they've been
nailed to the wall and the only thing
that's free to vary is the spin spin of
the electron a little Magnetic Moment
that it carries and now we have two of
them we have two of them and we're
interested in the space of states the
possible configurations of two
spins now again I can measure the spins
for example along the third axis and use
the measurements along the third axis of
the two spins
uh and I could choose the same axis just
for Simplicity I will choose to measure
them along the same axis and label them
very similar to the way I label the
single electron but now we need two
labels so for
example here's in fact we can write down
all of the states let me write down all
the possibilities we have in the first
entry here will correspond to the first
electron and the second entry will will
correspond to the second electron so
this means electron number one is up and
electron number two is up we will will
never get confused about which electron
is which one of the electrons is nailed
to the Blackboard over here the other
one is nailed over here and we call this
one and we call this two so there'll be
no confusion about which electron is
which this is electron one up electron
two up and then there's a state in which
electron one is down and electron two is
up and then there's another one in which
electron one is up but electron 2 is
down and then the last one down down
that's all there is those are all the
possibilities that we can get four
possibilities 2 *
two these
are the four possible states of two
spins and so we're evidently dealing
obviously with a four-dimensional vector
space now with four basis vectors uh and
two sets of quantities two sets of
observables now the two sets of
observables are of course the spins of
the two
electrons how am I going to label the
two spins of the electrons I can't call
them Sigma 1 and sigma 2 because I've
already used sigma 1 and sigma 2 for
something else for the two components of
the spin of one electron so I need
another name the first one I will
continue to call
Sigma the second one I'm simply going to
give another
name c follows Sigma in some alphabet or
other so we're going to label the first
electron Spin and just call
it Sigma it has three
components same as it had before Sigma 1
Sigma 2 and sigma 3 and the other one
I'm just going to label to and it also
has three components to one to two and
to
three how do the spin op operators for
the two electrons how do they operate
and what do they do to these
vectors let me let me teach you now how
you think
about first let's take the first
electron what does the spin operator
Sigma 1 and sigma 2 and sigma 3 due to
these four state vectors how does it act
on these four state vectors and here's
the answer if you're interested in the
first spin the one on the left here you
simply turn a blind die to the second
one you don't look at it it's passive
the operator Sigma which refers to the
first spin has no action on the second
electron it does nothing to it so when
Sigma acts it may or may not flip the
spin of the first electron but it leaves
the second one completely
unchanged all right that's the rule now
this rule of course is an empirical rule
but it sounds reasonable that the spin
of the first electron should only act on
the first electron on the on the
coordinate of the first electron so for
example Let's do let's do one or two
examples what
uh what does Sigma one do when it acts
on the state up down just as an
arbitrary example well you just turn a
blind eye to down and in fact when I say
you turn a blind eye I mean we will not
change the down for the second
electron
but we'll do to the first electron
exactly the same
thing that Sigma 1 did on the first
electron what did it do it flipped it
down so turning a blind eye to the
second
electron Sigma
one makes down makes makes the first
electron down has done nothing this the
second electron is completely
passive Sigma 1 does that okay uh let's
do uh another example just
to let's do Sigma 1 on down
down well again it does nothing to the
second electron and it flips the first
electron
up up
down okay so you see what I mean by
saying the second electron is passive uh
now let's ask about what Tao does too
are the operators associated with the
second
electron they also do something to the
state vectors this time you turn a blind
eye to the first electron and allow the
operator to act exactly the same way
except substitute Sigma for too exactly
the same way but as it applies on the uh
oh before I do that let me do one more
case of Sigma what about Sigma 3 on
let's take an arbitrary case up up down
what does this
give well Sigma 3 on up leaves up with a
plus one so it does
nothing up and the second one is passive
which just stays the way it is what
about Sigma 3 on down
down well you look over here on this
chart Sigma 3 takes down to down but
with a minus sign so it gives you minus
down down
in other words the second electron just
goes along for the
ride what about the tows the
tows act on the second electron and the
first electron goes along for the ride
so let's do one or two cases let's take
to
2 and act on up
down all right so to see what it does we
go over to the
Chart we're acting on the second
electron being down so we go over to
Sigma 2 on down and it gives us minus I
* up so this just gives us minus itimes
up up the first electron has been
passive nothing has happened to it the
second electron has responded exactly
the same way to Tao to to 2 as uh as
dictated by this chart
here that's a set of definitions that's
a set of definitions of what Sigma and T
do if you know what Sigma and to do to
all of the various vectors to all the
independent vectors then you also know
what it what they do to any linear
combination of them so this is a
complete
specification of how Sigma 1 and sorry
how Sigma and to all components of them
act on any
Vector
yeah that on the left table on the left
and it sort of slip by but now it's got
significant implications because the
minus is affecting both the electron
upus well multiplying a vector by an i
it doesn't matter where you put I mean
it doesn't make there's no meaning to
putting it inside the
vector uh you can multiply a vector by a
constant but the constant it's a
notational uh notation standard notation
to leave the constant on the outside of
the vector um another way the inside of
the T is just a label yeah it's a label
right right that's right it's a label
it's it's it's just a labeling
configuration it's not it it doesn't
make any sense to multiply the label by
a number so it goes on the outside but
yeah but you but you
are yeah I mean you wouldn't be able to
tell from this equation alone from this
equation alone whether this I was
because of this up or that up but if you
look at all the various possibilities
you know here's there's to 2 let's write
all the various things that to 2 can do
uh let's first do up
up uh so to
2 let's see that the um we have to see
to 2 on
up gives I * down so that's I *
down plus I * down and so forth we can
go through the list of them the point is
we know what Sigma and to do to every
one of the
vectors and so we know completely what
the nature of these operators are we
don't have to bother writing down
matrices we know what they do that's
enough for us uh for now we could invent
matrices describing them uh but it's
unnecessary for the moment maybe later
we'll do
it no it's it's just m well it's just
multiplication by I it's not physically
just it's just multiplication of the
vector by the number R it doesn't
represent any any rotation in real space
if that's what you're asking it does not
represent the rotation in real space
it's just the action of these matrices
so the matricies do and they just do the
same as they would have done had the
other label not been there that's
uh
now how
many over here this gentleman over here
remarked
before uh about the number of variables
that it takes to specify the state of an
electron and the answer was two the
answer was two independent real
variables that are important in
specifying the state of an electron okay
how many do you think it takes to
specify two
electrons that's what you think wouldn't
you okay but let's go through the
counting there's a four-dimensional
vector space you can where are they all
up up down up up down down down what
states can you build you can multiply
each one of these by a complex number
and add them all
together that's the most General State
of two electrons that you can write down
the linear combination of arbitrary with
arbitrary
coefficients sub je to the constraint
that the sums of the squares are equal
to
one and that the phase doesn't matter
now how many are
there what's the counting
now
six eight four complex numbers yeah we
have to we move two right right uh four
complex numbers that's eight variables
eight real variables remove two that
gives you six
right something's going on here there's
there seem to be more possibilities than
you might have guessed had you said each
electron itself can be in some state if
each electron was in some State each
electron requires two variables that
desine its physical state you might have
guessed the answer was
four okay um it seems that the space of
states must somehow be richer it must
contain things which are which cannot be
described simply as each electron having
its own State because there are just too
many variables just too many
possibilities instead of four there are
six so six variables six uh six
independent real numbers characterizing
the state of a two electron
system right this is
entanglement but first let me tell you
what corresponds to a pair of electrons
each with its own own State each with
its own State uh that you would
recognize uh as
a supposing the state of
the electron number
one or supposing we put the electron
number one in the state Alpha
up plus beta down and let me put a one
here to indicate that this is electron
one
that's electron one that's the state of
electron
one and now what about electron 2
electron 2 I'm going to write Alpha 2
time up plus beta 2 times down I'm not
going to write state of two state of
two now neither of these are really two
electron States two electron states have
to have two indices what what if
electron one is in this state and
electron 2 is in this state then the two
electron State you write down the
following way you write it as a product
alpha 1 up and then I'll tell you what
to do with it alpha 1 up plus beta 1
down times let's put a
bracket Alpha 2
up plus beta 2 down
and then read off from this the
following object alpha 1 Alpha
2 times both electrons
up up
up
plus alpha 1 beta
2 times the first electron up the second
electron
down then beta bet 1 Alpha
2 beta 1 * Alpha 2 * down
up and then finally plus beta 1 beta
2 down
down this two electron
State this two electron St state which
was obtained by combining two one
electron States
corresponds corresponds to a state in
which each electron is Comfortably been
placed in its own State sort of
independently that's what this
is if you were for example to take such
a
state you would
find that there is some Direction
in which Sigma 1 is definitely up
remember for any electron state that you
can make with an alpha and a beta there
is always some some direction in which
Sigma is sigma. n is up this state has
that property with the same just using
alpha 1 and beta 1 in the same way
you'll find a direction in space such
that Sigma 1 is definitely positive
it'll be the same direction as you would
have gotten by just looking at the one
electron system by itself same thing for
the two electron for the second electron
there exists some some direction a
different direction in general a
different direction in which the second
electron is also pointing along the
positive axis you can check that if
these two states have the property that
this one is definitely along the N axis
and this one is definitely along the ma
AIS then you can
check that the thing that you've
composed in this way has the same
property with respect to the more
complicated uh two electron system
remember Sigma 1 only acts on the UPS
sorry on the first electron Sigma to
sorry Sigma acts on the first electron
tow acts on the second
electron and you can check that uh that
this two electron state has all the
properties you would expect if you
simply had two distinct electrons that
have been prepared completely separately
never talking to each other
independently not necessarily in the
same state two different states for
example if you just put electron one in
magnetic field pointing this way and
electron two in magnetic field pointing
this way and let them come to rest and
let them give off their Photon and not
give off their Photon then that's what
this kind of state would be it's called
a product State it's a simple product
State and it always has a pair of
directions along which each electron is
polarized that's the word to say that
the electron has is definitely up along
some axis is to say it's polarized along
that
axis now I'm going to construct for you
a state which obviously doesn't have
that property which does not have the
property that there's some direction
along which the spin is up okay and it
is an entangled State it's one that does
not have the property that you can think
of it as two separate electrons which
have been prepared
independently each one with its own
State somehow the electrons are more
intricately
entangled the state of the electrons are
more intimately
in interestingly entangled here's a
state it's very simple
one electron is
up one electron is up the other electron
is
down and you add to that the first
electron down and the second electron up
of course you'll have to put a one over
Square < TK of two to normalize
it but that the one overun of two is not
going to play any role in what I say
here's a state and this state has the
property if you think about what the
state means it has the following
property that if you measure electron
number two and find its
down then electron number one must be up
and if you find electron number two up
then electron number one is down this
state has a funny property that you if
you know that it's in this state if you
have happen to know that it's in this
state the combined system then you would
learn something about the second
electron by measuring the first
electron okay all right this look this
state has the property that if you
measure the second electron to be down
then the first electron is up and if you
measure this the first electron second
electron to be up the second one is down
now the first one is down you know what
I mean I'm getting Tongue Tied it's
getting too
late
let me prove something to you let me
prove that every one of the sigma
matrices as well as the town
matrices has average value
zero in this
state remember how to calculate the
average
value you sandwich the operator that
you're interested between the state and
its uh and the state on the same state
on one side and the other
okay supposing it were true supposing
the expectation value of all three of
the sigmas was Zero then it will also be
true that the expectation value of any
Sigma do n will be zero if the
expectation value of Sigma NN is zero
that means that there's a half a
probability for it to be up along that
direction and a half a probability for
it to be
down so if all of the expectation values
of all three sigmas are equal to zero
then there can be no Direction along
which Sigma is definitely up because
along any direction the probabilities
are a half a half so let's see if we can
prove that let's take uh the three
sigmas and
check first of all we have to make a bra
Vector out of this all of the
coefficients are real so there's no
complex
conjugation we if one/ > of two is not
going to play any interesting role here
it doesn't do anything let's make the
correspond oning bra Vector the
corresponding bra
Vector also is the sum of two
terms and it's up
down plus down
up and now let's I don't know pick a
sigma let's start with Sigma
one Sigma 1 and then same state except
the K version of It Up Down plus down
up okay now we know how Sigma 1 acts
what does Sigma 1 do it acts on the
first entry here and it changes it
intertwines up and down that's all it
does it changes up to down in the first
entry and down to up so Sigma one on
this state here gives
us up goes to down down
down and takes this down and makes it up
other side here I've done nothing up
down plus down
up what's the inner product of up down
with down
down well I didn't tell you but the
answer is zero they correspond to
physically different situations where
one electron
which was up over here is down over here
that always means they're orthogonal
that always means they're
orthogonal different labels always
correspond to orthogonality up down up
up down down and down up are all
mutually orthogonal to each other that's
an assumption but uh but it goes
together with the idea that these are
measurable distinctly different
configurations so we have an up down and
a down up over here but no up down and
no down up over here so these must be
orthogonal everything here is orthogonal
to everything here and the inner product
is just plain zero you'll only get
something if there's something common
between the left between the bra vector
and the C Vector that's the only way you
can get something non zero that's the
expectation value of Sigma 1 what about
the expectation value of Sigma
2 what well Sigma 2 does about the same
thing that Sigma 1 does except it throws
in some I's and some minus
signs but still there's up down here and
down up over here there's only down down
and up up so it's still orthogonal this
is still orthogonal to this the
expectation value of Sigma 2 is zero we
found the expectation value of Sigma 1
is equal to zero the expectation value
of Sigma 2 is equal to Z the only one
left to Sigma 3 okay so let's check
Sigma
3 what does Sigma 3 do on
this
well keeps it up does nothing what does
it do with this
one minus
sign so Sigma 3 just multiplies this one
by
minus now let's look at the inner
product what's the inner product of up
down with up
down
one what's the inner product of up down
with down up they're different different
situations zero down up with up
down zero and up down sorry down up with
down down up with down up is one but
there's a minus
sign so we found all all
three expectation values are equal to
zero we've encountered a situation which
is impossible if every electron had its
own state in the same sense uh that it
would have a
state uh if as if there was just a one
electron system for any one electron
system there is always some axis such
that sigma.
n is equal to one that the expectation
value of sigma. n is equal to one and
incidentally in any igen uh in any IG
Vector of a quantity the expectation
value is just that igen value so there's
always some direction that Sigma n is
equal to one but if all three components
of Sigma have zero expectation value
then every Sigma doin expectation value
is equal to
zero so in every single Direction in
Space the probability is a half a half
to find uh to find the electron up or
down this is something new when we when
we concentrated on single electrons and
prepared them in magnetic fields no
matter how we prepared it with magnetic
field we found directions where the
electron spin was pointing in that
direction now when we have two
electrons in this interesting
state where measuring one tells you
something about the other we find
something new we find that there is no
direction or in every direction the
expectation value of Sigma is equal to
zero
equivalently any direction that you
measure the spin along you'll find 50/50
probability that it's either up or down
there'll be no bias toward upness or
down along any axis whatever which is
quite different than you might have
expected if you just had independent
electrons prepare them with magnetic
fields this is something new something
that cannot be if the only possible
states were the ones that were like just
having two independent electrons
prepared it's called an entangled State
and as I said the one way you can read
off that it's entangled is from the fact
that you if you measure one you learn
something about the
other okay now how odd a phenomenon is
this we're going to we're going to we're
going to dwell on this at length but
this is our first experience seeing
quantum
entanglement
you're trying to make I guess what I'd
call a direct measurement of the first
one
gives nonsense it's a thing but you
started off by saying well another way
to do this is to measure the spin of the
second
one and then you could say something
about the spin of the first one yeah
yeah yeah yeah two two separate things
making spend me spin of the second one
it's let's for a minute forget forget
the statement about measuring one and
learning
let's forget that for minut right so we
found the system that no matter what
direction you put the magnetic field on
electron one forget electron 2 no matter
what direction you impose the magnetic
field You'll Always Find 50/50
probability this is something that would
not have happened had you created the
electrons um independently by their own
magnetic
field it's another question how do you
create electrons in this
state uh in this state over here and
we'll come to that but for the moment
apparently in the mathematics there are
a collection of State vectors or a
collection of uh Quantum states which
have
properties that
no well that are
odd now they do have the property we're
going to come to this in a moment we'll
come we'll come back to it supposing you
measure
electron one and find it in some state
do you learn anything about electron 2
the answer will be yes and it will be
just as you might expect as I as I said
if you measure electron two up you will
find electron one down how odd is this
from a simple probability point of view
well in some sense it's not that odd in
some sense supposing I have you know a
penny and a dime okay and I take the
penny and a dime well let's suppose for
the moment that I uh that the penny and
the dime are exactly the same size so I
can't tell the difference with my hand I
take them and I shake them
up and without looking I grab one and I
grab the other and I take them far apart
guess what if I look at this one and I
find it's a dime I instantly know this
one as a
penny likewise if I look at this one and
I find it's a penny I instantly know
this one's a dime right without any uh
lag without any time lag so that's a
classical version of entangled
probabilities it's not all that
odd
uh
question or at least at first sight it
doesn't seem terribly odd the difference
well I think we'll come to it next time
what the difference is there is a
difference uh and we'll come to it but
just from a simple probabilistic point
of view let's say just measuring the
upness and down of electrons
at first sight it seems no
odder than the situation where I have a
penny and a dime I shake them up and I
don't look and I ask about the
probabilities when I take them apart you
know what first of all uh there'll be
50/50 probability that it's up or down
either one of them no matter which one I
look at if I only look at one of them
but if I look at one then I instantly
know what the other one does
only only if I'm sure that I had a penny
and a dime exactly and the corresponding
thing is true here only if I'm sure that
I've prepared the two electrons system
in this
state only if I'm sure that I've
prepared the two electron system in this
state question when you make the sigma 3
measurement you're you're measuring for
both of them being up is is that is that
what you're when you make this this when
you make a sigma measurement from on
both of them no no it's just a measure
when you make a measurement of both of
them of this of this pair of you might
and and the probability that they both
will be up is zero is that that is true
probability both is that it is true that
the probability of both of them up to
zero right because essentially they're
all pointing classically you would say
yeah I can tell you something else you
can define a new observable
quantity um the product of the two
sigmas well that's that's not a good
example um
this is not the right State okay let's
yes but but what you
huh
um no what I'm going to say is wrong um
but you what what is it that you said
you said that the uh that you're not
just measuring one of them and finding
the other one is in the opposite
direction you're measuring both in one
measurement and finding that both right
if you measure both in one measurement
you will find their opposite
but you could say you don't have to
measure them both
simultaneously you could measure one of
them over here and then your friend down
there doesn't even have to be you your
friend down there can measure the other
one and then you can communicate and
then you can uh come together and uh and
talk about what you discovered and so
forth you can be sure that if you
discovered a penny you can be sure that
when your friend comes over and tells
you what she discovered that it will be
a dime unless some something intervened
see it's like you had the PNY and the
dime mounted on a rod so that when one
of was heads up the other heads down and
you didn't see this Rod but no matter
how you shook it you would never get two
heads or two tails because they're
connected well there there are ways to
shake it that you might disturb it but
uh but I mean one of them would be up I
mean because they're they're welded
together uh well in the classical case
just started with a penny and a dime you
just know that that's always a penny
well I'm unless of course unless of
course some Alchemist takes the penny
and turns it into a
dime I me there's an assumption going on
here that
nobody yeah exactly
right um I T the law of large numbers to
find probabilities and statistical anal
yes and I was wondering what there is
about this that the law of large numbers
is not used for no no it no no we''re
using the law laws of large numbers in
many cases we're using the laws of large
numbers but at the moment I'm not but in
many cases when I say the expectation
value of something the expectation value
is something that you only measure by
doing many many repeated experiments and
Gathering data but in this very simple
case of the penny and the dime I need
only do one experiment if I do one
experiment and I find that Penny I know
that the other person will find a dime
now you may want to do this over and
over over again you may want to collect
data so you may want to do the same
experiment over and over and check that
it really works that every time I find
an A Penny she finds a dime every time I
find a dime she finds a penny so we
would uh perhaps like to do this
experiment over and over and over again
and check that statistically this
correlation it's called a correlation
that this correlation exists between
what she measures and what I measure and
it would be necessary to do it over and
over again and collect statistics about
it but what we should find is that every
single time we do it there will be we
could call it an anti-correlation
between what one person sees and what
the other person sees okay so
entanglement of probabilities is not
that odd a thing it just means you know
something about the combined system and
that that something doesn't get
Disturbed uh perhaps you separate the
things the odd thing is you could
separate the the two people one with a
penny and one with a dime take her off
to Alpha centuri where it takes four
years to get information from one to the
other nevertheless the instant I look at
uh my penny I know what U my friend out
there will
find she doesn't she doesn't but I do
you're not saying that that setup is we
should thinking about at a classical
level that's what you should be thinking
about but we're going to find that's
what Bell's theorem is about Bell's
theorem is about the difference between
the situation that I just described and
the corresponding Quantum
[Laughter]
system uh yeah but we know we know how
to make it if uh
this
yeah let me put a minus sign in here
it won't change anything nothing will
change uh we'll put minus
signs uh here but then it'll have
exactly the same effect okay uh that's a
better State okay here's how you make it
remember that each electron is itself a
magnet I'll first of all tell you what
this state corresponds to it corresponds
to the magnets being oppositely
oriented but without any but without any
preference for which direction all right
so so uh whichever way one magnet is
pointing the other one is pointing in
the opposite
direction and that naturally happens if
you bring two electrons uh if you bring
two electrons together because bringing
one electron into the field of the other
electron they naturally one electron
wants to respond to the other electron
and make its Magnetic Moment in the
opposite direction so if you brought the
electrons together in some wrong
configuration they would emit a photon
and jump to an opposite configuration so
all you have to do is bring the two
electrons together leave them for a
while a photon either will or won't be
emitted and after a while they will be
in this state they'll be in this state
because the two magnets will try to
anti-align each other but there's no
particular preference for them to
anti-align this way this way this way
and so uh you'll have something which is
the same in every direction but no
matter what direction you measure the
spin you'll find that the other one is
in the opposite
direction is
what yeah really that's right they and
just bring them together and leave them
for a
while and they'll go into this so-called
singlet State this is the singlet state
of two electrons yeah this the same
as no no no the moment there's no
Exclusion
Principle uh we don't have to think
about the Exclusion Principle for the
reason that we've definitely put the
electrons at different places in
space all right if they're in different
places in space then there's no issue
about uh about the PO Exclusion
Principle yeah yeah if you if you bring
them so that they wave yeah yeah yeah
but as long as they nailed down and we
know where they are you don't have to
bring them on top of each other you just
have to bring them close enough that
their magnetic
fields interact can feel each other and
then if the if the electrons are
parallel that's like having two magnets
which are parallel the North Poles repel
each other and it has more energy than
if they're
anti-parallel and so what'll happen is
is it'll a m a photon and somehow come
out uh come out with opposite uh uh
polarization and this is what will
happen to those two electrons so it's
really just using one electron as the
magnet which um which uh polarizes the
other
electron yeah so
electron of ELR yeah
of Electron Beam o oh oh oh well if you
have an
electron
um you have to all right if the
electrons are far apart from each other
and an electron beam the electrons are
very far no no they're very far apart uh
oh yes electrons Electron Beam is a very
very dilute
thing okay uh believe me electron
electrons are very very far apart by
comparison with the length scales inside
an
electron
cross they cross over you mean they hit
each other
no well if you have two beams of
electrons then
something they still don't get all that
close to each other they still electron
in a single beam to to a good
approximation they don't interact with
each other very much there is some Kum
repulsion between them but there's very
little spin spin interaction between
them they're too far apart it's too
dilute what's that what should be the
distance interaction ah okay the
Magnetic Moment has units of
length the Magnetic Moment is the
magnetic charge times the distance
between them okay so the Magnetic Moment
has units of length and that's the
length which sets the scale about how
close the electrons should be uh so in
other words they should be within that
uh within roughly within that uh
distance and then in a fairly rapid time
look it's a question of time scales no
matter how far apart the electrons are
they will a eventually settled down to
their ground state which was the
opposite uh eventually they will it's a
question of how long you're willing to
wait for the photon to get emitted so if
the electrons are far apart then the
difference between the energy of two
parallel ones and two anti-parallel ones
is so
tiny that the photon that's emitted is
such a long wavelength Photon it just
takes a very very very long time for
that uh for that process to happen so in
a typical Electron Beam there just isn't
enough time for uh for the electron
magnetic moments to feel each other very
much now of course if the electrons
Collide then then in fact you do make
States like this typically so that that
that does happen
but 10us 11 cm or something like
that
yeah why does that St have Aus sign
instead of the plus sign oh we'll have
to do that we'll we'll have to yeah now
that's that's by no means obvious that's
far from obvious
right right that's far from obvious I
will tell you but I'll tell you the
answer anyway I'll tell you the answer
anyway
uh no I
won't I'll talk the answer next time
time to go time to
go
[Music]
the proceeding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu